

## Huseyn Abdullayev

#### Data Scientist & ML Engineer

With several years of experience in data science and engineering, specializing in machine learning in the automotive and consulting industries, I can develop MLOps systems that automate machine learning workflows. My expertise in ML algorithms and optimization effectively contributes to cost reduction and time savings.

Petersberger Straße 25, 36037 Fulda
huseyn\_abdullayev@outlook.de
+49 (0) 1520 600 79 37
Huseyn Abdulayev

Huseyn Abdullayev

https://huseyna28.github.io/portfolio/

Professional Experience: 09/2023 - Present

#### **Junior Data Consultant**

It-novum GmbH

- Used Snowflake, Docker, GitHub Actions, and Jenkins to create end-to-end workflows that increased the efficiency of ML model development and deployment, while integrating MLflow for experiment tracking and model management to ensure reproducibility and transparency.
- Developed a dashboard in ThingsBoard that allows customers to track data sets and significantly improves data monitoring.
- Participated in a project to build an MLOps infrastructure for a client, including setting up a data cleaning pipeline and infrastructure for the data science team for training and monitoring models in Snowflake.
- Leveraged Snowpark to automate data loading and preprocessing in Snowflake, optimizing data
  processing and increasing scalability for large datasets, and integrated AWS services like S3 and
  Snowflake to provide scalable data storage and processing for extensive machine learning tasks.
  Deployed ML models with Docker to ensure reliable and reproducible deployments across
  development, testing, and production stages.

03/2023 - 08/2023

#### **Data Scientist**

AUDI AG

- Supported the modernization of the car manufacturing process by transferring production logic from Excel to KNIME data pipelines, reducing manual effort and saving 20% of preparation time per car.
- Developed an optimization algorithm for the supply chain department, improving resource allocation and increasing the efficiency of the production line by 25%.
- Created an XGBoost ML model for predicting engine resilience, analyzing key factors, and increasing prediction accuracy by 92%.

11/2021 - 03/2023

#### **Big Data Analyst**

SVA System Vertrieb Alexander

- Developed a LightGBM model on Azure Synapse Analytics with an R-squared accuracy of 0.92 to predict the number of bicycles per station, implemented on Azure ML.
- Achieved a 95% detection rate with minimal false positives in analyzing customer churn, leading to significant cost savings.
- Built a data pipeline for a terabyte-sized dataset using Azure Databricks and Azure SQL for data cleaning and storage, and Power BI for visualizations, increasing the reliability and accessibility of data by 50%.
- Participated in a project to create a customer segmentation analysis with RFM metrics in Azure, visualized with Power BI, helping the client identify and engage high-value customers, improving customer retention rates by 10%.

02/2020 - 11/2021

#### **Data Analyst**

Geschirr Box Kassel

 Analyzed customer data with Python and created a visualization dashboard that helped define target groups, enhancing marketing strategies.

# **Education:** 03/2019-06/2023

## Master of Science in Economic Behaviour and Governance

University of Kassel

- Field: Empirical Analysis in Economics
- Focus: Business & Finance Consulting

Grade: 2.3

10/2010-07/2014

#### **Bachelor of Science in International Economics**

Nakhchivan State University

• Field: Economics Analytics

• Focus: Economic & Financial Analysis

Grade: 1.9

#### **Further Education**

04/2024-07/2024

07/2023 -01/2023

07/2022 - 01/2023

04/2022 - 07/2023

04/2022 - 09/2022

01/2022 - 05/2022

05/2022 - 09/2022

Mlops-zoomcamp, Data TalksClub

• Inhalt: MLflow, AWS, Mage-ai, Docker, Evidently

Mlops Master Bootcamp. VBO

• Inhalt: Docker, Jenkins, MLflow, K8, FastAPI

Could Computing, The University of Texs at Austin

Inhalt: AWS, Azure, GCP AWS

Could Technical Bootcamp, VBO

• Inhalt: AWS Services, Linux, Cloud Network

Data Science Program, Practicum USA

• Inhalt: Linear Algebra, Time Series, Computer Vision, and Unsupervised Learning

Data Science and Machine Learning Bootcamp, VBO

• Inhalt: Python, SQL, Machine Learning models Advanced Big

Data and Data Science at Scale Bootcamp VBO

• Inhalt: Machine Learning in Big Data, Docker & Kubernetes, Pykafka, Pyspark, Linux, Git, Hadoop,

CI/CD and Jenkins, MLflow, Airflow, MongoDB

## **Projects**

- Snowflake MLOps: CI/CD, Github, Docker, FastAPI, Snowflake, LinearRegression | GitHub.
- AwsMlopsFaceApp Grafana, Snowflake, Docker, AWS, Snowflake, Railway APP GitHub.
- AdPredictor ML-deployment: CI/CD, Github, Docker, FastAPI, MI Model | GitHub.
- Sentiment Analysis with Deep Learning and MLflow: Python, Tensor Flow, Keras, Fast API, MLflow, Docker, MinIO, MySQL, Conda | GitHub.
- ML algorithms: Regression Models, KNN, Decision Trees, Unsupervised Learning, Gradient Boosting Machine and more | <u>GitHub.</u>
- Deploying ML on Docker&Kubernetes: Regression Model, FastAPI, Docker, Kubernetes, Minikube |GitHub.
- RFM Customer Segmentation: Python, Pandas, Scikit-Learn, RFM | GitHub.
- Time Series Analysis: Python, Prophet, XGBoost, Scikit-Learn, Statsmodels | GitHub.

#### **Medium articles**

- Automated ML Training and Deployment Using GitHub: CI/CD, Docker, FastAPI | Medium.
- End-to-End Machine Learning (ML) Lifecycle: ML Pipeline, Mage AI, CI/CD, Testing | Medium.
- The Role of Data Science in Sustainability Analysis: ML algorithms | Medium.
- Experiment Tracking with MLflow: Python, MLflow | Medium.
- Is Big Data Dead?!: Relevance of big data vs. small data | Medium.

# German English Azerbaijani Turkish

#### **Machine Learning Enginer**

MLflow, Azure ML, Pyspark, FastAPI, Snowflake, Docker, ETL, CI-CD, Model Deloyment& Monitoring, Ochestration, Experiemnent-tracking

#### **Data Science**

Python, Pyspark, KNIME, SQL, Deep Learning, Mode Evaluation, ML models, Linear Algebra, Statistics and Probability, Calculus

#### **Big Data Analyist**

EDA, KPIs, Power BI, Pyspark, NoSQL, SQL, A/B tests

#### Certifications

- SnowPro® Advanced Data Scientist
- SnowPro Core Certification
- Microsoft Azure Data Scientist (DP -100)
- Getting Started with Data Science (SAC)
- Basic Proficiency in KNIME Analytics Platform
- Advanced Proficiency in KNIME Analytics
   Diefform
- Data Engineering on Microsoft Azure (DP-203)
- Microsoft Azure Fundamentals (AZ -900)
- Microsoft Azure Data Fundamentals (DP-900)
- AWS Cloud Technical
- Databricks Lakehouse Fundamentals
- British Petroleum rewarded "Best Worker of the Year" in 2017